

Rashid Ali, Ph.D, CHRP

0304-3055277

House No. R/122, Gulshan-e-Qasim, Sector 34-A, Scheme 33, District Malir, Karachi-75270 rashidsharr@gmail.com

PROFESSIONAL ABRIDGEMENT

A **seasoned** Certified HR Professional with 20 years experience in the position and industries seeks to establish a career with this organization. Over the years, I have been involved in the growth and development of human resources in the companies I've worked with. I hope to share my experience and expertise with your company and contribute to the optimization of the human asset. An ideal combination of HR professional, Lawyer, Strategic thinking & Professional demeanor, with effective ability to manage diversified HR, IR and its Administration. Analytical problem-solver with the ability to manage projects & operations independently while liaising with the top-tier management, not limited to the following;

- HR Policies & Procedures
- Legal Drafting /JDs
- Contract Administration
- Recruitment & Retention
- Employee Relations / CBA
- Reengineering

- Sustainable Training
- Performance Management (i.e. Hay Methods)
- Compensation Administration

SKILLS SUMMARY

- Professional Certified Human Resources Professional (CHRP).
- Proficient in Labour, Employment, Corporate and Environmental Laws.
- Proficient in Legal, Contract and Manual drafting.
- More than 20 years of HR experience in Manufacturing, Textile and Service Industries.
- In-depth knowledge of SESSI/ EOBI/Welfare laws and practices.
- Excellent interpersonal, Decision-making, Problem solving skills.
- Excellent written and oral communication skills.
- Proficient in MS Office, SPSS and HR systems software such as Workable.
- Quality Management System ISO:9000, CSR, HSE,

EDUCATION & QUALIFICATIONS				
2010 - 2015	Ph.D.	University of Sindh, Jamshoro Major: HRM , Department of Public Administration		
2008 - 2010	M.Phil. (Leading to Ph.D).	University of Sindh, Jamshoro Major: HRM 3.8 GPA		
2006 - 2007	CHRP	NED University, Karachi & PIQC, Karachi Major: HRM - Certified Human Resource Personnel		
2003 - 2004	MBA	PMSAT, Karachi (Executive Program) Major: HRM 3.7 GPA		
2001 - 2003	LLB.	University of Sindh, Jamshoro Major: The Major Laws		
1989 - 1992	MA	University of Sindh, Jamshoro Major: Economics		
1987 - 1989	BA	University of Sindh, Jamshoro Major: Economics		
2014 - 2015	COR. Law Course	Islamic Islamabad University Major: Islamic Law & Finance		
EMPLOYMENT				
October 2007 - May 2019	GM - HR	Hasham Group		
February 2006 - October 2007	Manager - HR	Avari Towers		
June 2004 - February 2005	Manager - HR	Dewan Group		
August 1998 - June, 2004	Manager - HR	Hasham Group		
July 1994 - May, 1998	Warden - HR	Emirates Airline Emirates		

OCCUPATIONAL CONTOUR & ACHIEVEMENTS

- Work with superior to strategically plan HR initiatives that will benefit the company and encourage more efficient and beneficial work from employees and arrange suitable direct hiring and training procedures for new employees. Provides support and assistance to top management team on handling and resolving Human Resources issues.
- My role is responsible for ensuring the effective and consistent delivery of human resources services including: coaching/counseling employees and management, sourcing and selection, performance management programs, organizational effectiveness, compensation and providing HR leadership.
- Schedules screening, verifies validity of all submitted identification materials and documentation including social security / EOBI. Specific activities include but are not limited to executing service delivery systems, creating integrated solutions to business problems or issues, acting as an employee and company advocate that can balance decision making appropriately.
- Manages and updates personnel files for old and new hires in the Human Resources Information System database. Ensures that all hiring and recruitment processes are in compliance with all companies' policies, regulations and provincial labour laws laws.
- Continually educate employees on company policies (including sexual harassment, appropriate dress, grooming, safety and social media permissions, etc.) and keep employee handbook current & updated.
- Administered or change benefits, health plans, retirement plans, etc and monitoring employee progress and stay abreast on company climate and culture, ensuring it stays positive and productive
- Coordinates and direct work activities for officers and employees, foster cross-functional relationships and ensure managers and employees are properly connected
- Regularly meet with employees for progress reviews and assessments, discussing any problems or grievances they may have. Also promote a positive and open work environment where employees feel comfortable speaking up about issues
- Manage and supervise other HR staff, ensuring they are assigned and carry out proper tasks and understand and adhere to all pertinent laws.
- Maintained operational efficiency, e.g. adequate staffing, streamline job roles, staff development, task-specific training, general training, up-skilling, continuing professional development. Prepared job description, e.g. job role, prerequisites (skills, experience, license, hours, location).

- Managing employment procedure (appraisal, promotion, grievance, maternity, sickness and absence, disciplinary, redundancy, termination, retirement) and comply with employment legislation, labour laws, criminal record checks, data protection and verifications.
- Neutralized CBA/Union pressure with amicable and peaceful manners. Restored management confidence and authority through mutual trust and repair the trust deficit between the CBA/Union employees. Strengthen forma/informal relationship with Media, Interest Groups and Community.
- Successfully negotiated on numerous charters of demands, concluded bilateral agreements and settlements between CBA & Management in mutual interest and benefits.
- Initiated severance packages a 100% employer paid benefit plan which included initiating a payoff schedule for a final savings of 16% to the organization. Resuscitated struggling organization by reducing overstaffed workforce by 10%, addressing and resolving compliance issues and facilitated all stakeholders/parties.
- Created computerized data bank (HRIS-inventory) and maintained data of 1500 employee with all demographic, family, educational, professional, skills, Reward & Punishment, BMI, Health and EOBI, SESSI and Personal File record.
- Introduced and implemented RCA (Root cause analysis) FRCA (Failure of root cause analysis), Selection & Recruitment policies, Harassment /Cellphone/Messing policies, Performance Management Criterion Procedures, ER / IR policies and Disciplinary Procedures, Rightsizing Principles (Lay off Techniques), effective and merit-based succession planning, Career path and Performance management utilized HAY Method.

PROFESSIONAL PROFICIENCY

• Selection & Recruitment & Decision-making Skills: I strongly consider people as invaluable assets and selection & recruitment is the key processes in any organization and it is how the business/organization sources and acquires its most precious assets. The paramount aim of recruitment is to appoint someone who can do the job you want and filled to the required standard of performance. Therefore, having vast experience of job designing, job rotations, job enrichment and consequently hiring a right person for the right job at the right time is my valuable quality in my credit. I select and got appointed numerous dynamic incumbents from lower management to paid director/general managers. Conducted and prepared HR manual, Skill inventories and several psychometric tests including but not limited to Occupational Personality Questionnaires, Differential Aptitude Tests (DAT) and Structured interview design.

- Labour, Civil, Corporate laws, Environmental Laws and Liaison with Government officials & Problem-Solving Skills: Enjoying very good relationships with the high-ups of federal Government, GB and all four provinces including personal relations with civil and armed forces high ranks. I have capacity and quality to make friends and always rise for the organization's favour in the critical situation. Being a registered Advocate of High Court, having practical knowledge of labour, civil, corporate, environmental laws and HSE dependently designed, drafted, and implemented many Cases, Manual, SOPs, Contracts, Agreements, and Charters in the interest of the organization, employees, and stakeholders. My ability to analyze a problem, develop suitable strategies and display independent thought has allowed me to successfully work in distinct areas of social conflicts.
- Payroll, Time Management, and People-Project Management Skills: Surely, an individual's evaluation of a job opportunity is based on more than just current pay. It also includes the benefits that a company might offer, as well as the opportunities for learning and advancement: the career. In assessing the rewards being offered by a company to its current and prospective employees, it is important to understand the relationship among these three important reward components. Since, I have served as an executive in different organizational at Management level positions and as an HR & Administrative Manager, I have supervised more than 1500 persons and various projects, both in the day-to-day running of the project and its overall planning, which has yielded valuable data.
- Training & Development: I strongly believe that training and development are all about letting people gain knowledge, practice their skills, and hone their attitudes. The three aspects together are often referred to as competence. In this connection, I have conducted more than 55 training seminars, workshops, lectures and research papers presentation and implemented training and development programs for future talent in alignment with goals and objectives of the department and organization. Further, I have initiated and devised progressive disciplinary proceedings with assurance so that those proper grievance-handling methodologies are observed.
- Quality Management and OD: Being a procedure owner and MR of Quality Management System in the certification of ISO: 9001-2015 and personal interest in applied emotional intelligence and ergonomics, having sufficient knowledge about the latest quality management techniques and tools. Succeeded in creating a congenial and trustworthy corporate culture, conflict resolution in the organization to promote a harmonious relationship from the Top management to the Worker. Also handled administrative procurements and contractual affairs.
- Job Evaluation / Performance Management: Clear performance goals according to G.R.O.W and SMART models, proper delegation, coaching and feedback supported by the routine performance appraisal system and to give authority down the level in order to wring out maximum productivity from the available employee's population.

Job evaluation of work for the purpose of determining the relative value of jobs within an organization fashioned on the notion that jobs can be measured on the basis of their relative contribution to the overall objectives of the organization.

n	Course	Year	Institute (venue)
1	Awareness of Quality Management System	2011	Bureau Veritas (BVQI)
2	Best OHS and CSR Practices	2011	CPI (Cleaner Production Institute)
3	Challenges facing managers in the era of globalization	2012	EFP, Karachi
4	Communication Skills	1999	EDC Network, Karachi
5	Dine like a Diplomat Business Dress	2006	Etiquette House, Dubai
6	EOBI & SESSI Provincial Scenario	2017	ILO & Ministry of Labour
7	EPA Self-Monitoring	1999	EPA, Directorate, Karachi
8	Framework for Economic Growth of Pakistan	2011	University of Sindh
9	HR Strategy Forum	2005	Geo, Pakistan
10	Internal Auditing to Quality Management System	2014	SGS, Karachi
11	Introduction to ISO 9000 & Internal Quality Audit	1999	Quality Concerns
12	Introduction to RE Policy 2013	2016	Alternative Energy DB, Islamabad
13	ISO 9001:2015 Internal Audit & NCRs	2018	BVQI, Karachi
14	Labour Laws & 18 th Amendment	2017	ILO & Ministry of Labour
15	Legal Domestic Enquiry	2001	Bureau of Labour Publications
16	Management Concepts	1999	EDC Network, Karachi
17	Management Development Program	2000	University of Karachi
18	Managerial Skill Development	2004	Skill Development Centre
19	Planning for Higher Productivity	2010	Franklin Covey Co.
20	Seven New Tools of Quality	2011	National Productivity Organization
21	Strategic HRM	2003	PIMS
22	Succession Planning Employee Development	2011	Employee Federation of Pakistan
23	Total Quality Management	1999	PIMS

PERSONAL INFORMATION

STATUS: MARRIED AND FIVE DEPENDENTS

DATE OF BIRTH: JUNE 20, 1968

HOBBIES: READING, TRAVEL, TEACHING AND RESEARCH.

LANGUAGES: FLUENT IN ENGLISH, URDU, PUNJABI, AND SINDHI.